<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sitzExtase</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://www.sitzextase.de/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.sitzextase.de/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2015 12:53:55 +0300</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2015 12:53:55 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Text Encoding Fundamentals and their Application</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Context: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dhsi.org&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Summer Institute&lt;/a&gt; 2015, UVic, 1-5 June 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slides are available &lt;a href=&quot;/slidesDHSI2015/index.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;course-description&quot;&gt;Course description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This five-day course will provide a hands-on introduction to digital editing practices and tools employing a set of XML-based technologies: The Extensible Markup Language (XML) istself (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/TR/xml11&quot;&gt;specifications&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XML&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.), the XPath data model (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/TR/xpath-datamodel/.&quot;&gt;specifications&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XPath&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.), the declarative language to transform XML (Extensible Stylesheet Language Transformations, XSLT)(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/&quot;&gt;specifications&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XSLT&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;), and finally a specific “dialect” of XML, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml&quot; title=&quot;the TEI Consortium&#39;s Website&quot;&gt;Text Encoding Initiative’s TEI P5&lt;/a&gt;. The course will cover the process from the original creation of digital files using TEI XML to retrieval of data and publication to the web using XSLT. 
We will do so on the basis of late nineteenth-century manuscripts of British diplomatic correspondence from Damascus and the first bi-lingual, English and Arabic, weekly newspaper published in the USA, &lt;em&gt;Kawkab America&lt;/em&gt;. Digital images, as well as sample encodings will be provided. 
Finally, we will problematise the applicability of the TEI to non-European languages written in non-Latin scripts, particularly Arabic and Ottoman.
No previous programming skills or knowledge of mark-up languages is required, even though previous experiences are an advantage. The course will be adapted to the needs of registered participants.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sitzextase.de/teaching/2015/06/01/TEI-at-DHSI/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sitzextase.de/teaching/2015/06/01/TEI-at-DHSI/</guid>
        
        <category>teaching</category>
        
        <category>TEI</category>
        
        <category>XML</category>
        
        <category>XSLT</category>
        
        <category>markup</category>
        
        <category>newspapers</category>
        
        <category>Arabic newspapers</category>
        
        
        <category>teaching</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>From analogue documents to electronic texts: Introduction to TEI XML editing in multilingual environments</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Context: &lt;a href=&quot;https://dhibeirut.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Institute - Beirut&lt;/a&gt; 2015, AUB, 2-6 March 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slides are available &lt;a href=&quot;/slidesDHIB2015/index.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;course-description&quot;&gt;Course description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This five-day course will provide a hands-on introduction to digital editing practices and tools employing a set of XML-based technologies: The Extensible Markup Language (XML) istself (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/TR/xml11&quot;&gt;specifications&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XML&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.), the XPath data model (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/TR/xpath-datamodel/.&quot;&gt;specifications&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XPath&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.), the declarative language to transform XML (Extensible Stylesheet Language Transformations, XSLT)(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/&quot;&gt;specifications&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XSLT&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;), and finally a specific “dialect” of XML, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml&quot; title=&quot;the TEI Consortium&#39;s Website&quot;&gt;Text Encoding Initiative’s TEI P5&lt;/a&gt;. The course will cover the process from the original creation of digital files using TEI XML to the publication of XML files using XSLT. To do so in a meaningful way, each participant will encode a single issue of one of Beirut’s many newspapers covering the restoration of the Ottoman constitution in summer 1908.Finally, we will problematise the applicability of the TEI to non-European languages written in non-Latin scripts, particularly Arabic and Ottoman.
No previous programming skills or knowledge of mark-up languages is required, even though previous experiences are an advantage. The course will be adapted to the needs of registered participants.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sitzextase.de/teaching/2015/03/02/TEI-at-DHIB/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sitzextase.de/teaching/2015/03/02/TEI-at-DHIB/</guid>
        
        <category>teaching</category>
        
        <category>TEI</category>
        
        <category>XML</category>
        
        <category>XSLT</category>
        
        <category>markup</category>
        
        <category>newspapers</category>
        
        <category>Arabic newspapers</category>
        
        <category>manuscripts</category>
        
        
        <category>teaching</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>XSLT functions for converting calendars</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I came across the necessity of converting Islamic &lt;em&gt;hijrī&lt;/em&gt; dates to Gregorian dates in order to automatically harvest data from the Baṣbakanlik Osmanli Arṣivi’s catalogue into my research database. Unfortunately the database I use (the reference manager Sente) is proprietary software that can only deal with Gregorian dates. Thus, I needed to translate a certain string through XSLT in order to produce the correct XML for import into the database. I soon discovered that even though, formally the specifications for the format-date() function in XPath 2.0 include the &lt;em&gt;hijrī&lt;/em&gt; calendar (labelled “Islamic”) and even Arabic month names, this specification was never actually implemented.
As I could not find any available code on the net, I adopted the javascript conversion between Gregorian, Julian, and Hijri calendars provided by John Walker’s Calendar Converter for XSLT 2.0 and decided to share the functions on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tillgrallert/xslt-calendar-conversion&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; for reuse.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sitzextase.de/2014/02/28/xslt-calendar-conversion/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sitzextase.de/2014/02/28/xslt-calendar-conversion/</guid>
        
        <category>XML</category>
        
        <category>XSLT</category>
        
        <category>calendars</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The puzzle continues II: in addition to *al-kabīr* and *al-ṣaghīr*, *al-Muqtaṭaf* published slightly different editions in Beirut and Kairo</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am just about to fix the references in my thesis, and a possible reason for differences between available copies of &lt;em&gt;al-Muqtaṭaf&lt;/em&gt;, which I had briefly mentioned in my first post &lt;a href=&quot;http://sitzextase.de/2012/12/29/the-historians-puzzle-various-differences-between-copies-of-printed-periodicals-that-ought-to-be-similar/&quot;&gt;on the issue of differences between copies of printed periodicals that ought to be similar&lt;/a&gt;. As I wrote shortly &lt;a href=&quot;http://sitzextase.de/2013/08/19/the-puzzle-continues-al-muqta%E1%B9%ADaf-was-printed-in-two-different-and-unmarked-editions/&quot;&gt;thereafter&lt;/a&gt;, the scholarly community had just not read &lt;em&gt;al-Muqtaṭaf&lt;/em&gt; close enough to discover the existence of a long (&lt;em&gt;kabīr&lt;/em&gt;) and short (&lt;em&gt;ṣaghīr&lt;/em&gt;) for Volumes 6 to 9, which were most likely targetted at two different markets (the long version at Egypt and Europe and the short one at Beirut, Lebanon, and surrounding areas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, the original puzzle had been the absence of a short note on the publication of the three new periodicals &lt;em&gt;Dimashq&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;al-Salām&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;al-Iʿtidāl&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;http://sitzextase.de/muqtataf/muqtataf-v04-i05.html&quot;&gt;some copies of the fifth issue of volume 4&lt;/a&gt;. Upon closer inspection of the front covers to copies of volume 4, I found the same difference in annual subscription prices and that those copies lacking the short article, carried the note “Printed at &lt;em&gt;al-Muqtaṭaf&lt;/em&gt; Press in Egypt on the expense of founders and Shāhīn Makāriyūs, the owner of the press”. We can thus establish the existence of an “Egyptian” and a “Syrian” edition already by June 1878 (the publication date of the first issue of volume 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://sitzextase.de/muqtataf//img/v04/pr02/um/muqtataf-v04-pr02-um-covers1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image1&quot; /&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://sitzextase.de/muqtataf//img/v04/pr01/up/muqtataf-v04-pr02-up-covers1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I have not had access to different editions of volume 5 (the covers of copies SOAS, Michigan, and Princeton show no differences), but I suspect it too exists in (at least) two editions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2014 13:57:30 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sitzextase.de/2014/01/19/the-puzzle-continues-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sitzextase.de/2014/01/19/the-puzzle-continues-2/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The puzzle continues: *al-Muqtaṭaf* was printed in two different and unmarked editions</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I noted at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sitzextase.de/2012/12/29/the-historians-puzzle-various-differences-between-copies-of-printed-periodicals-that-ought-to-be-similar/ (The historian’s puzzle: various differences between copies of printed periodicals that ought to be similar.)&quot;&gt;end of last year&lt;/a&gt;, Ottoman and Arabic periodicals of the late nineteenth and early twentieh century appeared in different editions. Print-runs differed in spelling, pagination, lay-out, and content. However, I was not aware of the extend of this phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just discovered that the journal &lt;em&gt;al-Muqtaṭaf&lt;/em&gt;, published by Yaʿqūb Ṣarrūf and Fāris Nimr under the directorship of Shahīn Makāriyūs in Beirut until 1884, printed two “first print runs” or first editions” (&lt;em&gt;al-ṭabaʿat al-ūlā&lt;/em&gt;), whose content differed by exactly 32 pages per issue! Copies of the twelve issues of volume 7 (1882-83) available at many European and Middle Eastern libraries comprise 760 consecutively numbered pages, while the copy at Princeton library, digitally available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://hdl.handle.net/2027/njp.32101007749409&quot;&gt;Hathitrust&lt;/a&gt;, comprises only 344 equally consecutively numbered pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate the issue, let’s have &lt;a href=&quot;http://sitzextase.de/muqtataf/muqtataf-v07-i01.html&quot;&gt;a look at the first issue of volume seven (June 1882)&lt;/a&gt;. The first 16 pages of the two editions are identical. Page 17 of the copy at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.orient-institut.org/&quot;&gt;Orient Institut Beirut&lt;/a&gt; (OIB) is the first page of a lengthy tracte on “women’s rights” (&lt;em&gt;ḥuqūq al-marʾa&lt;/em&gt;) by Wadīʿ Efendi al-Khūrī. In the Princeton copy, the same page 17 comprises four short questions (&lt;em&gt;masāʾil&lt;/em&gt;) and the beginning of the section &lt;em&gt;bāb tadbīr al-manzil&lt;/em&gt;. Both pages bear a printer’s mark with information on the volume, the edition, and the binding block. While volume number and edition are marked as identical, the number of the binding block differs: “3 ṣ” at Princeton, “3 k” at the OIB. To my astonishment, the OIB copy continues with the same paragraph of the &lt;em&gt;bāb tadbīr al-manzil&lt;/em&gt; section on page 48, after which the two editions are again identical, save for the page numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The printer’s marks provide a solution to the riddle in the case of &lt;em&gt;al-Muqtaṭaf&lt;/em&gt; – or rather, they provide an indicator for the edition one is looking at. After having checked further volumes at the OIB (vol. 6-9), the volumes comprising “extended” issues of 64 pages all bear the Arabic letter &lt;em&gt;kāf&lt;/em&gt; in the printer’s mark, while the “short” issues of 32 pages were marked with the latter &lt;em&gt;ṣād&lt;/em&gt;. In addition, those copies whose index survived the times (at least 6-9), show that the index took account of a “large &lt;em&gt;Muqtaṭaf&lt;/em&gt;” (&lt;em&gt;al-muqtaṭ af al-kabīr&lt;/em&gt; in Arabic and abbreviated by the &lt;em&gt;kāf&lt;/em&gt; in the printer’s mark) and a “small &lt;em&gt;Muqtaṭaf&lt;/em&gt;” (&lt;em&gt;al-muqtaṭaf al-ṣaghīr&lt;/em&gt; in  and abbreviated with a &lt;em&gt;ṣād&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon further investigations, it turned out that the two editions weren’t exactly completely “unmarked” beyond the printer’s mark on the binding blocks and the indexes. The cover sheet for the short and the extended version differ in the quoted prices and location of subscription:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The extended version quoted prices for annual subscriptions “in Europe and the Egyptian lands” at £1, while&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the short version quoted annual subscriptions at “Beirut and Lebanon” at Frcs 7 and Frcs 8 for the surrounding areas (&lt;em&gt;al-jihāt&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A systematic comparison of the two editions, the existence of which hitherto escaped the scholarly community, might reveal and equally systematic targetting of themes to different audiences. This could mean that major scholarly works on the Nahda, the press, and its audience need substantial reworking.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2014 13:39:09 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sitzextase.de/2014/01/18/the-puzzle-continues/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sitzextase.de/2014/01/18/the-puzzle-continues/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The historian&#39;s puzzle: various differences between copies of printed periodicals that ought to be similar</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the recent days I discovered that contrary to myexpectations libraries around the world hold numerous unmarked editionsand print-runs of the first series Düstur (&lt;em&gt;tertib-i evvel&lt;/em&gt;). Copies vary in pagination,spelling, and content. Yet, neither the people I asked nor the scholarlyworks citing copies of Düstur, seem to be aware of significantdifferences between copies of the same volume.  In consequence, it isalmost impossible to confirm references found in scholarly literature.Over the past years I had come to consider the many seemingly wrongreferences in Aristarchi and Young as, well, erroneous references bycareless printers, copy-editors, even the translators themselves, but asit stands, they could have just used a different copy.
As I could not readily find any concordance or works dealing with thisissue (which by the way also pertains to nineteenth century Arabicmonthly journals), I wondered whether anybody on various mailing lists could point meto relevant information. Düstur was the official collection of Ottoman legal texts at the time and the differences between the various print-runs had potentially grave consequences. Yet, to my surprise (again) nobody in the scholarly community of Ottomanists seems to be aware of these puzzling divergences and no reply had any answers to offer.
To illustrate the issue, I quickly built a simple website providingimagery for different versions of the table of contents of the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://sitzextase.de/dustur/dustur-v01.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sitzextase.de/dustur/dustur-v03.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;third&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://sitzextase.de/dustur/dustur-v04.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;fourth&lt;/a&gt; volume of Düstur, as well as for a page of &lt;a href=&quot;http://sitzextase.de/muqtataf/muqtataf-v04-i05.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;al-Muqtaṭaf 4(5)&lt;/a&gt;. Please have a look at them and if any of the readers has access to further versions of the mentioned periodicals, I would appreciate a comment below or via &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tillgrallert&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Update 12 Jan 2013] The index to the first series of Düstur, published in 1891 as Ḳaraḳoç, Sarkiz. &lt;em&gt;Miftāḥ-i Ḳavānīn-i ʿOŝmāniye&lt;/em&gt;. Der-i Saʿādet: Maḥmūd Bey Maṭbaʿası, 1309 aH [1891], does not contain any information on divergent print-runs and editions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Update 19 Jan 2013] Safa Saracoglu solved at least part of the riddle, by pointing out that, before &lt;em&gt;Düstur&lt;/em&gt; became a series from 1872 onwards, three independent volumes were published under the same title in in 1851, 1863, and 1866.  Hence, what I thought of as the first edition of the first volume of the first series of &lt;em&gt;Düstur&lt;/em&gt; was indeed the 1863 volume.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2012 14:24:43 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sitzextase.de/2012/12/29/the-historians-puzzle/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sitzextase.de/2012/12/29/the-historians-puzzle/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Digitised German newspapers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After the relaunch of the &lt;a href=&quot;http//:www.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de&quot;&gt;Staatsbibliothek Berlin&lt;/a&gt;’s website, I stumbled over the &lt;a href=&quot;http//:zefys.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de&quot;&gt;ZEFYS&lt;/a&gt; project or Zeitschrifteninformationssystem, a very long and technically sounding German composite term. Newspaper Information System is, at least to me, a bad choice, when it comes to a digital humanities project and possible search strings needed to be found on the internet. Despite being oddly named, it is truly brilliant: out-of-print German newspapers are digitized and provided through a unified interface to manyfold repositories (i.e. co-operating libraries). In addition, viewing software &lt;a href=&quot;http://dfg-viewer.de/en/&quot;&gt;DFG Viewer&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://dfg-viewer.de/fileadmin/groups/dfgviewer/METS_Anwendungsprofil_2.0.xml&quot;&gt;metadata structure&lt;/a&gt; (METS, MODS XML) are open source and provided under GPL. Thus, a high level of interoperability is provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huzzah! Future home for possible post-doc project(s)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not yet. At the moment, the presentation tool of the DFG viewer is tailored to the broader public as only the image files are accessible; marked up xml files are &lt;strong&gt;not provided&lt;/strong&gt; for download – heck, they are not even provided to the human eye reading the website. 
Some of the core collections (e.g. Prussian Gazettes) have been properly marked up with person and place names and the enhanced data is accessible through the &lt;a href=&quot;http://zefys.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/en/amtspresse/&quot;&gt;ZEFYS own webinterface&lt;/a&gt;. However, again, the xml source files are not available to the public.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2011 01:00:34 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sitzextase.de/2011/08/24/digitsed-german-newspapers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sitzextase.de/2011/08/24/digitsed-german-newspapers/</guid>
        
        <category>resources</category>
        
        <category>newspapers</category>
        
        <category>digitized sources</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
